Guide to the Improved Housing Association of New Haven Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Improved Housing Association of New Haven records
1911-1920
MS 1310
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The records, which include correspondence, financial and legal papers, checks, and printed matter, are incomplete; they begin in 1911, when the association was incorporated, and end in 1920. They consist of two separate files, one kept by the secretary and one by the treasurer, as well as some general and miscellaneous papers. The collection does not contain Schwab's records, nor De Forest's, nor the minutes of the directors' meetings. The general papers include prospectuses describing the work of the Improved Housing Association of New Haven, and numerous summary financial statements. These papers are arranged chronologically, while both the secretary's records and the treasurer's are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Secretary Berman's records include correspondence with the National Housing Association, and with other "model home associations" and "workingmen's dwelling enterprises" in various cities. There is also correspondence with the association's officers and supporters, and materials describing its formation and work. The treasurer's records, which form the bulk of the collection, are mostly from Day's tenure. They constitute a detailed financial record of the association, documenting the rental and maintenance of its houses, as well as its sales of stock, acquisition of further real estate, and tax payments.
Improved Housing Association of New Haven
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Improved Housing Association of New Haven, which include correspondence, financial and legal papers, checks, and printed matter, are incomplete; they begin in 1911, when the association was incorporated, and end in 1920. They consist of two separate files, one kept by the secretary and one by the treasurer, as well as some general and miscellaneous papers. The collection does not contain Schwab's records, nor De Forest's, nor the minutes of the directors' meetings.
The general papers include prospectuses describing the work of the Improved Housing Association of New Haven, and numerous summary financial statements. These papers are arranged chronologically, while both the secretary's records and the treasurer's are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Secretary Berman's records include correspondence with the National Housing Association, and with other "model home associations" and "workingmen's dwelling enterprises" in various cities. There is also correspondence with the association's officers and supporters, and materials describing its formation and work. The treasurer's records, which form the bulk of the collection, are mostly from Day's tenure. They constitute a detailed financial record of the association, documenting the rental and maintenance of its houses, as well as its sales of stock, acquisition of further real estate, and tax payments.
The provenance of the records is unknown.
Biographical / Historical
The Improved Housing Association of New Haven was an organization which attempted to provide model houses for working people. Modeled on similar associations in London, Glasgow, New York, Philadelphia, Washington, Boston and other cities, it was a response to the living conditions found in urban tenement houses at the beginning of the twentieth century -- overcorwding, dampness, darkness, poor ventilation, dirt, garbage, poor sanitary conditions, and disease, especially tuberculosis. It was not a charity but a stock association; as Irving Fisher explained to the New Haven Chamber of Commerce in 1914, "The proposition is to meet the bad landlord on his own ground by providing better tenements than he can offer and educating the public to demand them, proving that good tenements pay and making bad tenements fail to pay."
New Haven's association was incorporated in May 1911, on the recommendation of Lawrence Veiller, secretary of the National Housing Association, who visited the city in July 1910. Early in 1914 the association opened a block of eight two-family "model houses," which it had built, and which it continued to rent and maintain. According to city directories, the organization continued to exist until 1948. Its early officers were John C. Schwab, president; Charles S. De Forest, vice-president; Barnett Berman, secretary; and Frank B. Frisbie, treasurer. George Parmly Day succeeded Frisbie in 1916; and in the same year Schwab died, and the association, unable to find a replacement, functioned without a president. The original directors of the association were Schwab, De Forest, Susan S. Farnam, Irving Fisher, Edwin S. Greeley, George L. Hendrickson, and Emma Winner Rogers. The stockholders included a number of prominent New Haven citizens.
Housing -- Finance; Working class; Connecticut; New Haven (Conn.); Labor movement; Labor; Improved Housing Association of New Haven; National Housing Association (U.S.)
- Inventory
  - General, 1911-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Secretary's records
    - A-F, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - G-O, 1911-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - P-Y, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's records
    - A-B, general, 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Berman, Barnett, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - C-G, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - H-M, general, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mechanics Bank of New Haven, 1911-1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mechanics Bank of New Haven, 1917-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 12)
    - N-T, general, 1913-1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Trowbridge, Hattie B., 1915-1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Trowbridge, Hattie B.: rent statements, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - United States Internal Revenue, 1912-1920 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - United States Liberty Loan -Y, 1914-1919 (Box 2, Folder 17)